Okay בוקר טוב, boker tov, חודש טוב. chodesh tov. Today's דף daf
is ע"ו, ayin vav, 76. We pick up at the bottom of
ע"ה עמוד ב. ayin hey amud bet. We were dealing with the
whole, the משנה mishna that picks up as a question: the husband
stipulated that his wife doesn't have blemishes, and it turns out she
has blemishes. There's the whole, then the question is: did she have
these before קידושין, kiddushin, before the giving of the ring, and then
the condition was not satisfied and she's not married, or after the
giving of the ring and therefore she is married? And the big
difference is if she's married, then he could divorce her, but a,
he would require a גט get and b, he would get her
כתובה. ketubah. So that's the issue. And the משנה mishna basically said
that it depends whether the blemishes were found when she was in
her father's house before the חופה, chuppah, or after she was in
her husband's house after the חופה. chuppah. If she's in her father's
house, it's her burden of proof; when it's in her husband's house,
it's his burden of proof. It wasn't exactly clear why any of
that should make a difference, and the first answer of the גמרא
Gemara was basically: you're right, the משנה mishna sort of are two
separate opinions stapled together, which is a very strange answer. Now the
גמרא Gemara gives a different answer. So we pick up on the
bottom of ע"ה עמוד ב ayin hey amud bet and the גמרא
Gemara says like this, middle of ע"ה
עמוד ב,
ayin hey
amud bet, the
גמרא Gemara says: רבא אמר, Rava amar, thank you, רבא, Rava,
it's about
two-fifths of the way from the bottom, about 20 lines from the
bottom. So רבא אמר, Rava amar, רישא, reisha, the beginning where they're
found in the father's house and it's her burden of proof or
the father's burden of proof, is because we say כאן נמצאו כאן
היו—here kan nimtzu kan hayu they were found, here they probably occurred.
Which is an interesting idea, which means since the blemishes were found
in the father's house, we should assume that they were pre-existing. Okay,
they, we found them when she was, like he really goes into
two, you know, stages: she's with her father, living with her husband.
If they're found in the, in her, in the father's house—I mean
figuratively in the father's house, right—then we assume she had them from
growing up and therefore that's the assumption. So if she wants to
prove that they came after the קידושין, kiddushin, she has the burden
of proof. כאן נמצאו כאן היו. kan nimtzu kan hayu. סיפא, seifa,
and that's why. Whereas if they're found in the husband's house, we
assume that they occurred once she was in this husband's house, and
he has the burden of proof to prove they were earlier. Such
an interesting presumption, not exactly clear what the logic is, but okay.
And סיפא נמי, seifa nami, כאן נמצאו כאן היו. kan nimtzu kan
hayu. And in the end they're found in the husband's house, we
presume that they occurred in the husband's house. So somehow based on
which sort of status she's in—you know, being part of her father's
house or being part of her husband's house—the signs when we're going
to assume this thing cropped up. We see it now: if it's
in father's house, we assume she's always had it; in husband's house,
we assume it's recent. All right, so אביי Abaye asked, אביי Abaye
asked רבא. Rava. At least some logic, even if we don't fully
like get it, at least it helps explain the difference in the
משנה. mishna. So אביי Abaye asked on רבא: Rava: נכנסה לרשות הבעל,
nichnesa l'reshut habaal, here's what the משנה mishna says: once she got,
had the נישואין, nissuin, went into the husband's domain, נכנסה לרשות הבעל
הבעל צריך להביא ראיה שעד שלא תתארס היו בה מומין אלו הרי
המקח מקח טעות. nichnesa l'reshut habaal, habaal tzarich lehavi rayah she'ad she'lo
titars hayu bah mumin elu, ha'mekach mekach taut.
So what if it's now the husband's responsibility? What does he have
to prove? He has to prove that those blemishes existed from before
the קידושין kiddushin and therefore the קידושין kiddushin was an error, okay?
Because that's what it means, it's the husband's now burden of proof,
to prove that the blemishes existed prior to the קידושין. kiddushin.
So עד שלא תתארס, ad she'lo titars, אם, im, you have to
prove that they were there from before the
קידושין. kiddushin. משתתארס, לא, mishetit'ares lo, it's not enough to prove that
they were there from after the קידושין kiddushin took place. So why
is that true? Why shouldn't that be enough?
עד שלא תתארס, ad she'lo titars, אם, im, משתתארס, Mi'she'titars, לא, lo,
ואמאי, ve'amai, why is that not enough? לימא כאן נמצאו כאן היו.
leima kan nimtzu kan hayu. Why not say: here's where they occurred,
here's where they were found, here's where they occurred? Which means the
following: maybe it'll help with a diagram for some of that, okay?
So here she is in her father's house—I don't know how you're
going to make it her father's house, it's just smoke coming out,
anyway, the time. Yeah, exactly. Here she is, okay, that's her dad,
I don't know how you're going to see the difference between the
dad and the
husband, okay, אבא, Abba, okay, anyway, fine. Okay. And then, so then
anyway, somewhere here there's the ring, there's the הרי את מקודשת לי,
harey at mekudeshet li, okay, מה לי, mah li, anyway, there it
goes, it's in the משנה, mishna, no, anyway,
so
that's
the,
anyway. And she stays in her father's house and then here's the
חופה. chuppah.
Okay and here they are standing under the חופה. chuppah. It's lovely.
Okay. Okay. And then that's that's that's the her father's house and
this is the the groom's house. Okay. The בעל. baal. The רשות
הבעל. reshut habaal. Okay. So,
so, here's the story. It says if she goes ahead and discovers
the מום mum when when if the מום mum is here discovered
here when she's in her father's house, okay, that's where I discovered
the מום mum and right here he made the קידושין. kiddushin. Here
he said על מנת שאין עליך מומים. al menat she'ein alayich mumim.
Okay. And then it was discovered here when she was still in
her father's house. Okay. So we say our presumption is כאן נמצאו
כאן היו. kan nimtza'u kan hayu. They were found in the father's
house, כאן היו, kan hayu, so they were always with her and
it's going to presume that she was married she already had the
מום. mum. And she has the burden of proof to prove that
it happened afterwards if they were found in the father's house. If,
however, they were found here, then we assume oh כאן נמצאו כאן
היו, kan nimtza'u kan hayu, it was found here that's when it
occurred. So presumably it occurred after the קידושין, kiddushin, it occurred in
the רשות הבעל. reshut habaal. And if the husband wants to prove
that the marriage is no good, he has the burden of proof
to prove they came earlier. That's what the משנה, mishnah, that's how
Rashi explains the משנה. mishnah. Here's however אביי's Abaye question. אביי's Abaye
question is: let's say it was in this case. And now because
it was found once she went into the רשות הבעל, reshut habaal,
it's assumed that's when it cropped up and he has the burden
of proof to prove it came earlier. Why does why does he
have to prove he's got to prove it came from here, okay,
that's what he has to prove. Says אביי, Abaye, why does he
have to prove it came from before the קידושין? kiddushin? Why don't
he just prove that it came while she's still at her father's
house, like let's say somebody saw saw her with this blemish while
she was in her father's house? Why don't he just prove it
came here and then we'll say oh once he's proven that it
was seen in her father's house, כאן נמצאו כאן היו kan nimtza'u
kan hayu and then we'll assume that it occurred even from before
the קידושין. kiddushin. But once the logic is that if it's discovered
in the father's house then presumably they were always with her, so
when he has the burden of proof why do you have to
prove that it came from before the קידושין? kiddushin? Just prove that
it was discovered that it was seen in the father's house, right,
while she was still in her father's house and we'll go oh
once he's proven it was seen in the father's house we'll presume
that it always was with her. And what do you get from
it? I'm getting a lot of blank stares. Okay, so that's אביי's
Abaye question. So you explained that here the presumption is that it
was before and she has the burden of proof. Here the presumption
is that it's now and he has the burden of proof, he
the husband. But okay, he has the burden of proof, but then
prove that it came during this period and then that allows us
to add to that the presumption that it came from earlier. It
should be enough to show that it came from that period, not
necessarily that it came before. So that's אביי's Abaye question. So let's
see where they go.
איבעיא להו לאביי, Ibaiah lehu leAbaye, אביי Abaye asked: נישאת לבעל, nisait
labaal, once she's married to the
husband, הבעל צריך להביא ראיה שעד שלא תתארס היו בה מומים אלו,
habaal tzarich lehavi re'ayah she'ad shelo tit'ares hayu bah mumim elu, that
that the it's the husband's burden of proof to prove that these
blemishes happened from before
the קידושין. kiddushin. ונתארסה בטעות, venit'arsah betaut, and it was an error.
So עד שלא תתארס אין, ad shelo tit'ares in, yes, from before
since he has to prove from before it existed before the קידושין.
kiddushin. משתתארס mishetitars, לא, lo, not sufficient to prove that it happened
that
it was seen after the קידושין. kiddushin. ואמאי, ve'amai, why wouldn't it
be sufficient to prove that it was seen after the קידושין? kiddushin?
ולימא, velayma, let's once you prove that it was seen sometime while
she was still in the father's house, what if you add to
that the presumption and say כאן נמצאו כאן היו, kan nimtza'u kan
hayu, here they were found, here they cropped up. So the גמרא
Gemara says אמר ליה, amar leh, so רבא Rava says back to
him: משום דאיכא למימר חזקה אין אדם שותה בכוס אלא אם כן
בודקו. mishum de'ika lemeimar chazaka ein adam shoteh bekos ella im ken
bodeko. והא ואתה נישאת. veha ve'atah nisait. So says no,
because if you know all he does is he proves that it
was seen over here, then we'll say fine it was seen over
here but we're going to presume since it was seen over here,
you actually married her, right? So good, you've proven it was seen
over here. If you've proven it was seen over here we're going
to presume that you saw it also. And if you saw it
also and then you went through with the marriage, so that must
mean that you were okay with it. Got it? Meaning if it
was discovered here and there was no חופה, chuppah, you could say
aha it's discovered, I don't want to marry her, and we're going
to assume that I want to assume I'm going to assume that
it was back that it already had the מום mum from back
here. That's that case. So then that's the presumption and she has
to prove otherwise because he wants to call it off over here.
But here he's going through with it. So if all you do
is prove that it existed over here, then we're going to say
okay great you've proven it existed over here but you went through
with the wedding. So since you went through with the wedding we're
going to say that it's not enough to prove it existed over
here we're going to say you missed it. What? What if it
was not... let's not let's not go... okay? But he somehow was
able to demonstrate it, that meant that it was discoverable and if
it was discoverable that it existed here we're going to assume that
you discovered it and if you went through with the wedding that
meant you were okay with it. So that's why once the חופה
chuppah to place, it's not enough to show it existed over here,
because then he, doesn't matter it existed here, he went into the
wedding. Okay, so let's read that again.
Alright. וחזקה אין אדם שותה בכוס אלא אם כן בודקו. Vechazakah ein
adam shoteh bechos ela im ken bodko. A person doesn't drink from
the cup unless he checks it out. You're not going to go
through the חופה chuppah unless you've done your due diligence. והא עביד
חופה. Veha avid chuppah. Therefore, since in this scenario you've gone through
with the wedding, it's not enough to prove that it existed at
that stage because you were okay with it. So why go through
with the wedding? וחזקה דמאי. Vechazakah demai. But wait a minute, if
that's true, that once he goes through with this חופה chuppah then
it shows that it doesn't matter that there was a מום mum
because he went through with it, אלא הכי השתא נמי. ela hachi
hashta nami.
So then how does it do him any good to prove it
existed way back here? Like if you prove it was way back
here, it wouldn't matter. It was a מום mum that was discoverable.
You went through with a חופה, chuppah, that shows you're okay with
it, right? So it doesn't matter it existed when he went through
the חופה, chuppah, he loses any right to claim that there was
a problem, right? So if even when he went through the חופה,
chuppah, if it was demonstrated that the problem existed before the קידושין,
kiddushin, we could say the קידושין kiddushin was no good, etc., then
even why is it enough to demonstrate it across here, and then
we'll presume that it existed before the
קידושין? kiddushin? Yeah? What are you
saying? Isn't there some kind of a
duty to
check it
out? Yeah, so of course that's the point, you know, which is
that you're right. I mean, okay, maybe, maybe the counter-argument is he
won't be okay with it, but maybe, you know, he's got more
responsibility to demonstrate that. There is a חזקה, chazakah, there is a
חזקה chazakah that he, you know, that he did know about it
since it was knowable and that he was okay with it. You're
right. I mean, so the point is it's totally reasonable to say
that even though חזקה אין אדם שותה בכוס, chazakah ein adam shoteh
bechos, if it was something that he knew about or he could
have known about, we're just going to assume that he did know
about it. Okay? But the point then is, is that if that
were true, then any time there's a חופה, chuppah, he loses all
rights. Okay? And that's not what we say. Right? We say even
after there's a חופה, chuppah, if he proves that it was from,
if it really was the problem, he wins. So why not just
prove it's here? Right? Once we say that there are counterbalancing arguments
in terms of what the חופה chuppah actually means.
So this סוגיא sugya in a sense is a סוגיא sugya about
competing presumptions. Yeah? Right.
Well yeah, exactly. I know, but I can't find חזקה דגופא. chazakah
degufa. I know, but so many points. I know.
No, but the whole thing is the interplay of the legal force
of competing presumptions.
Yeah, you're absolutely right. And I'm going to say something about the
fourth presumption in a minute, but the presumption of... ah. So let's
see what the גמרא Gemara says. Okay.
אלא. Ela.
אלא משנתארסה. Ela mishenitarsah. So now exactly the גמרא Gemara is going
to be very, very explicit about exactly what Rabbi Joe just said.
הכא נמי הכא נמי אלא חזקה אין אדם שותה בכוס הכא נמי
חזקה אין אדם שותה בכוס. Hacha nami hacha nami ela chazakah ein
adam shoteh bechos hacha nami chazakah ein adam shoteh bechos. So therefore
in the same way, the getting married doesn't, doesn't, like, make him
lose his claim if he proved it existed before קידושין, kiddushin, it
shouldn't make him lose his claim if it presumes that it existed
after, supposed to be existed after the קידושין. kiddushin. Once we can
assume that if it's found in the father's house, we'll assume that
it existed beforehand,
then that's going to continue to be a good point here. Okay?
And just having done the חופה chuppah doesn't make him lose his
claim. So
אלא משנתארסה. ela mishenitarsah. Here's why he doesn't have a claim once
they have the חופה, chuppah, once if the מומים mumim were discovered
after the קידושין. kiddushin. but he
demonstrated that there were מומים mumim, *mumim* from in the father's house.
משום דאיכא תרתי *Mishum de'ika tarti*, there are two things that are
in favor of the woman. Number one, חזקה chazakah... המעמיד הגוף אחזקתו
*Chazaka hama'amid ha'guf achezkato*, assume that the body has its presumptive state,
and we'll assume that these are new blemishes, I mean, new that
she wasn't born with them. So therefore, the assumption since she wasn't
born with them, we'll assume that he only got them at the
latest stage possible. That's the חזקת הגוף Chazakas HaGuf *chazkat ha'guf*. The
body didn't start with these, so we'll assume they came as late
as possible. וחזקה vechazaka. אין אדם שותה בכוס אלא ela, אם כן
בודקו *Ve'chazaka ein adam shoteh be'kos ella im ken bodko*, and the
presumption that no one goes through with the חופה chupa, *chuppah* unless
he knew what he was getting himself into. והאי ראה ונתפייס *Ve'hai
ra'ah venitpayes*,
so and he saw and he was okay with it. Okay, so
when they're found here, okay, we basically say there are two things,
see, he discovered it here. He has the burden of proof. If
he just proves that they existed here, we can say okay, but
there are two things that argue in her favor. Number one is
her חזקת הגוף Chazakas HaGuf *chazkat ha'guf* makes us presume that it
occurred as late as possible, so that pushes us on saying that
we'll assume it happened only after the קידושין kiddushin, *kiddushin*, they were
found after the קידושין kiddushin. *kiddushin*. The חזקת הגוף Chazakas HaGuf *chazkat
ha'guf* reinforces that, makes us assume as late as possible. That's one
thing that argues in her favor. חזקת הגוף Chazakas HaGuf *Chazkat ha'guf*
argues after the קידושין kiddushin, *kiddushin*. And the other thing that argues
in her favor is he went through with the wedding. Okay, one
minute, we've got to see the counterargument. מאי אמרת *Mai amart*, what
will you say that's on his side of the equation? חזקה chazakah
אין אדם מתפייס במומין *Chazaka ein adam mitpayes be'mumim*, that no, the
guy went through with the wedding, he wouldn't be okay with the
fact that there are blemishes. הא איכא חד במקום תרתי *Ha'eika chad
bemakom tarti*, it's one against two. וחד במקום תרתי לא אמרינן *Vechad
bemakom tarti lo amrinan*, and one against two, we don't say. עד
שלא תקבל המעמיד הגוף אחזקתו *Ad shelo tikabel hama'amid ha'guf achezkato*, no,
so, okay fine, that's point number one. So basically, if it's found
here, okay, the fact that he went through with the חופה chupa,
*chuppah* is an argument in her favor. The fact that אין אדם
מתפייס במומין
*ein adam mitpayes be'mumim* sort of neutralizes that. So those two arguments
are neutralized. Fine. So the חופה chupa, *chuppah* aspect is neutralized. But
what she does have in her favor is חזקת הגוף Chazakas HaGuf,
*chazkat ha'guf*. If it's found here, and the חזקת הגוף chascas haguff,
*chazkat ha'guf* reinforces the likelihood that it, right, that it was not
earlier, that it was only when it was found. Right, let's just
finish this argument. That's when he, that's when it's found here and
he proves it occurred here. עד שלא תקבל *Ad shelo tikabel*, but
if he proved that it existed here, okay, עד שלא תקבל המעמיד
הגוף אחזקתו לא איכא למימר *Ad shelo tikabel hama'amid ha'guf achezkato lo
eika lemeimar*, then you can't say, oh, her חזקת הגוף chezkas ha-guf
*chazkat ha'guf* proves that it's after, you know, reinforces that it was
after the קידושין kiddushin. *kiddushin*. He's demonstrated that it was before the
קידושין kiddushin *kiddushin*, right? He's demonstrated the problem really existed. Okay, so
when he proves it here, the problem clearly existed. Now you have
to somehow prove that it's not a problem. So, מאי איכא *Mai
eika*, what could you say? חזקה chazakah, אין אדם שותה בכוס אלא
אם כן בודקו *Chazaka ein adam shoteh be'kos ella im ken bodko*.
Ah, so what she can say is although you proved that the
problem was here, you went to marry me unless you were okay
with it. נו והאי ראה ונתפייס *Nu ve'hai ra'ah venitpayes*, and you
must have been okay with it. No, אדרבה *aderaba*, חזקה chazakah אין
אדם מתפייס במומין *chazaka ein adam mitpayes be'mumim*. No, that's neutralized by
the presumption that a man wouldn't be okay with blemishes, especially if
he stipulated. ואוקי ממונא אחזקתיה *Ve'oki mamona achezkatei*, and therefore he's to
me, as you want to take the money away from him, you've
got to prove it. So basically what it says is like this:
the idea that he went through with the חופה chupa, *chuppah*, okay,
and that should be
a mark in her favor, is neutralized by the counterargument that a
guy isn't going to be okay with a blemish, especially if he
stipulated against it. So basically the argument for and against her gets
neutralized, okay? So when he demonstrates that it's here, she is, it's
presumed to be here because she has a חזקת הגוף chezkas ha-guf.
*chazkat ha'guf*, so she wins, okay, even though she's coming to take
money away from him. When he demonstrates it's here, she has nothing
in her favor, right? We've presumed that the חופה chupa, *chuppah* is
neutralized with the אין אדם *ein adam*, you know, that a person
isn't okay with the blemishes. So when it's shown here, when it's
shown there, it really is a מקח טעות *mekach taut*. Okay, so
that's how the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* has basically answered it. Now, תוספות
Tosafos *Tosafot* asks, wait one second, תוספות Tosafos *Tosafot* asks, basically, what
you have done is you've neutralized the meaning of the חופה chupa
*chuppah*, right? That's what you've done. You've neutralized the חופה chupa, *chuppah*.
One argument is in her favor, one argument is in his favor,
you've neutralized it. So it's down to the fact that if you
prove it's here, obviously the guy's going to win, and if you
prove it's here, she's going to win, okay? So תוספות Tosafos *Tosafot*
back to question number one, why is it any different when it's
actually found in her house? When it's found in her house and
it's over here, we don't say the חזקת הגוף chezkas ha-guf *chazkat
ha'guf* makes her win. We say כאן נמצאו כאן היו kan nimtzu
kan hayu, *kan nimtze'u kan hayu*, if it's found in her house,
we assume that it came from before. So we're back to square
one. Remember that's where we started. We started why when it's found
in her house before there was ever a חופה chupa *chuppah*, does
he have the, does
they have
the, does the... So even if there was a חזקת הגוף chezkas
haguf that would reinforce the idea that it was after the קידושין,
kiddushin. we say no, it's found in the house, we assume it
always has it. So we're back to square one. So same the
same thing here. It was found after the חופה, chupa he discovered
it, he can prove it existed here. We want to say חזקת
הגוף reinforces it was late. Whatever happened to the argument that כאן
נמצאו כאן היו, kan nimtzu kan hayu. right? It's a good question.
So there's going to be like a lot of moving of the
pieces around, but then we're back to the question. It says, okay,
where does the חזקת הגוף that makes her win? So does חזקת
הגוף work even if it was found, you know, in her house?
So here's תוספות Tosafos says. תוספות Tosafos. says, says listen to what,
and this gets into the four חזקות. chazakos. תוספות Tosafos, says in
this case where there was already a נישואין, nisuin, there are four
things that counteract each other, right? One is presumably if you would
have gotten married through חופה, chupa it proves you're okay, against that
is אין אדם מפייס במומין, ein adam mefayes bemumin, right? And the
other thing is this issue about, like, there's a חזקה... chazakah. there's
a חזקת הגוף and against that is the חזקה chazakah of... of...
כאן נמצאו כאן היו. kan nimtzu kan hayu, So there's all these
things that counteract each other, right? Going through חופה, chupa but it
proves you're okay, against that is אין אדם מפייס במומין. ein adam
mefayes bemumin. Finding it here is a חזקת הגוף, but against that
is
another... is כאן נמצאו... no, כאן נמצאו כאן היו, okay? So what's,
תוספות Tosafot says what's the difference? In the case where they went
through the חופה, chupa in order for him to win the case,
he has to be... he has to prove both points. He has
to win both, it's like an 'and' or an 'or'. Two things
have to be true for him to win in this case. Number
one is he has to show that he wasn't okay with it,
just going through with the חופה, chupa right? He has to... that
has to be number one. And number two is he has to
say that כאן נמצאו כאן היו, it must have occurred from before.
For her to win, only one of those has to be correct.
Either it's enough that even if she had the problem, it's enough
that going through
the חופה chupa shows he was okay. Or it's enough that she
didn't have the problem, right? That the problem occurred only afterwards. So
that's why this is better. In this case, where they went through
the חופה, chupa, as soon as they went through the חופה chupa,
it's like, okay, it's neutralized and we're back to square one. If
he went through the חופה chupa now, in order for him to
win, two conditions have to be met. You have to show that
going through the חופה chupa does not mean that he was... that
he was okay with it, that he was מוחל. mochel. I understand.
But the point is, for him to win, 'A' and 'B' have
to be true. 'A' has to be true, that going through the
חופה chuppah. does not mean he was okay with it, and 'B'
has to be true, that the problem existed prior to the קידושין.
kiddushin. For her to win in this case, only... not 'A' or
not 'B' has to be true. I'm not doing propositional logic, 'A'
and 'B'... not 'A' or not 'B'. Either, right? For her to
win, either, maybe the condition did exist earlier, but going through the
חופה chuppah, shows he's okay. Or the condition didn't exist earlier. So
that's why in this case, she's going to win unless he can
prove it existed from before. The weight of the חופה chuppah doesn't
just get automatically neutralized from a counter-argument. It means that he has
to prove two things now. He has to have two things to
be true in order for him to win, whereas if they didn't
have חופה chuppah. yet, he only has to be... one thing to
be true because they didn't have חופה, chuppah, which is that it
was found here, we're going to presume it existed earlier. But as
soon as he went through with the חופה, chuppah now he's got
to prove that two things are true in order for him to
win, and that's why until he can prove it occurred back here,
he's going to lose. Yes? Next question is this. I mean, if
we seem to be applying this to מומין, mumin, to me it
doesn't make sense to do that. The only thing you can really
see that happening is the מומין, mumin, that can happen any time.
Right. Right. Even some נולדו, noldú, so we're saying that we're always
just talking in a case where it's something that is not congenital.
Okay. Now, of course the question is, is it not clear whether
it's congenital or not? Okay. And then... so I want... I'll read
the תוספות. It's וחזקה. If you look at the
first wide line of the middle-sized lines of תוספות, the first middle
line, middle line he says: ויש לפרש דמשום הכי כי הוי תרוייהו
בהדי הדדי אלימא טעמא דאשה משום דאפילו לא יהא אלא אחד מהם
אמת. v’yesh l’faraish d’mishum hachi ki havei tarvaihu bahadi hadadi alima ta’ama
d’isha mishum d’afilu lo yehei ela echad maihem emes. As
long as only one of those things to be true. או חזקת
הגוף, O chazakas haguf, which makes it show that the problem came
after the קידושין, kiddushin או אין אדם שותה בכוס, o ein adam
shoteh b’chos, or
the
fact that there's a חופה chuppah, shows he was okay. As long
as one of those are true, she wins.
So in that case, יש לה כתובה. yesh lah kesubah. אבל בעל,
Aval ba’al,
for him to say that he's out of the problem, לא מיפטר
אלא אם כן תרוייהו, lo mipatar ela im kein tarvaihu, he has
to have 'A' and 'B' to be true, אמת. emes. שאם אחד
מהם שקר, She’im echad maihem sheker, if
one of them is false, either the חופה chuppah, shows he wasn't
okay with it or the... The problem came after the קידושין. kiddushin
מה עושה הבעל? mah oseh ha-ba'al? הוא קלקל טעמי הבעל וטעמי האשה.
hu kilkel ta'amei ha-ba'al v'ta'amei ha-ishah.
Very blatant. Okay. So, yeah, it is a big difference adding this
in. In the end, if you just had this part, the whole
question would be did it come here, did it come earlier, and
we're going to say ספק ספיקא, s'fek s'feika, then that's enough to
make us assume it came earlier, and so he can't win in
terms of trying to get money out of him. Okay, but if
you had this element, now only for her only one of
two possibilities have to be true, whereas for him, both possibilities have
to be true. Yeah, exactly. Not only to get money in a
property
case
you have to have the preponderance of evidence on your side.
Yeah, but this is, this is sounding like, if you think of
it as a property case, the guy might not be winning because
it's super complicated. Yeah, but he's also, it's sort of like a
ספק ספיקא, s'fek s'feika, right? If you sort of think about it
that way, right? It's like a ספק ספיקא, s'fek s'feika, right? It's,
you know, for you to be right, both A and B have
to be right, for me right, so A and B,
I mean we don't, we don't use a logic of ספק ספיקא
s'fek s'feika by like ממון, mammon, but, you know, that certainly would
seem like a preponderance of evidence. That's what this is saying. You
have a lot of things in doubt, but for the, you know,
if you just want to do a, let's assume everything is a
fifty-fifty likelihood, right, then for A and B to be true, you
have only twenty-five percent of, of the likelihood, right? And for any,
you know, for any other combination, it's a seventy-five percent chance. So,
yeah. I have two questions. One, how does one prove or disprove
that he's reconciled or not reconciled with a מום? mum? We don't.
That's why I'm wondering about this piece. No, but because he says
that there's another possibility, it gives more weight to her side. But
this, this whole thing about this did not happen, like in court,
everybody presents their arguments. It was serial, I mean the last thing
that occurred was the חופה. chuppah So all of the, all the
responsibility of being בודק bodek should come just before the חופה, chuppah.
really should, should... Right. Well you're basically just saying, the fact that
they had a חופה chuppah shows you're okay. But basically imagine what
happens, they come the next morning into court, he says I discovered
these מומים, I explicitly made a תנאי, t'nai, that's it, the קידושין
kiddushin, was never חל, chal, the whole thing is off, I don't
have to pay off כתובה. k'tuvah. And she says, no, first of
all, this only מום mum only happened after whatever, after the קידושין.
kiddushin Number two, buddy, you went through with the חופה. chuppah That
shows you knew what you were getting into and you're okay. No,
I never knew, it was a מום mum I wouldn't have known,
and they all, they argue it all out. Now how is he
supposed to pay, which is which? So basically that's what the ריצבא
Ritzba says, he's got, she has a lot, he has a lot
more to prove to say that, that there was no קידושין מעיקרא
kiddushin m'ikara than she does.
Okay, well so then this goes back to my question. So then
being reconciled or accepting of a מום, mum, it's a personal thing.
I mean how can you have like a general rule for it?
So, you
know,
I mean that's an interesting question, right, about like whether you could
bring like, you know, conversations that he had, other types of things
to show whether he would have been okay or wouldn't have been
okay, but I don't know, I don't know if that other was
intended to be proved, you know, whether אין אדם שותה בכוס ממונו
ein adam shoiteh bekhis mammono or אין אדם פייס. ein adam piyes.
My sense was was that because these are like counter-arguments in theory,
that just means that it shifts the burden of proof. Therefore if
you the guy want to prove after you've gone through with the
חופה, chuppah because there's a possibility that that signals that you're okay
regardless, if you want to win this case, you're going to have
to prove it in much more absolute terms. You're going to have
to prove that it existed before the קידושין. kiddushin. Proving that it
existed after the קידושין kiddushin. is not going to be enough to
win because the fact that you went through with the חופה chuppah,
sort of shifts more the burden of weight of evidence on you.
So that might be without sort of saying like, you know, two
things true, one thing true, an easier way to say the חידוש,
chiddush, once you've gone through the חופה, chuppah. that signals that you're
okay, so if you now want to prove that it never was
good, you got the burden of proof, she doesn't
have the burden of proof. Is it okay, so then how does
the marriage dissolve, since one of these two... no, do we say
there was no marriage because the תנאי t'nai was, if the תנאי
t'nai depends where it is. Either way, it's out a case of
כתובה k'tuvah
or not, but it's always צאי. tzei. צאי Tzei means that if
he divorces her he pays the כתובה, k'tuvah, doesn't mean that there's
no marriage. You have to give her a גט. get. Okay, and
he could choose not to. All right, so that's basically, so the
easy way, I mean this argument really boils down to, I mean
it got confusing, but if you just think about it in terms
of burden of proof, what it boils down to is the following:
when the, when the problem is found in her house, then it's
assumed that she's got the burden of proof. Once he goes through
it because she's trying to take money, you know, get money from
him. Once he marries her, then there's a presumption that maybe you're
okay with it anyway, and therefore the burden of proof shifts to
be his burden of proof, okay, since this gives us a presumption
that hey, it could be he was okay with it even if
there was a problem. So if he wants to actually argue that
there's a, he wants to show that it becomes now his burden
of proof. That's Rav's view. Now the גמרא Gemara comes on. It
says like this, רב אשי אמר, Rav Ashi amar, רב אשי Rav
Ashi says here's the explanation of the difference, whether
it was found in the husband's house or in... רישא Reisha in
the first case where it where he has the burden of proof,
מנה לאבא בידך. mana l'abba biyadeich. If she's still in her father's
house, it means that she's a minor, conceptually she's in her father's
house, it's not just that there's no נישואין, nissuin, but it means
she's still a קטנה ketana or a נערה. na'arah.
So who gets the כתובה? ketubah? The guy got to marry a
woman and divorce her, קידושין kiddushin. and גירושין gerushin without נישואין, nissuin,
just קידושין, kiddushin she's still in her father's house, and then divorce,
who gets the כתובה? ketubah? The father gets the כתובה. ketubah. So
therefore in this case when it's found in his house and then
he says, oh my god, there was this מום, mum, forget it,
I don't want to marry you, the קידושין kiddushin, never caught. She's
like what do you mean, of course it caught, so I only
got this מום mum later. So she's basically saying she knows what
happened to her body. She says I know when I got this
מום, mum, I got it later. But she's arguing on behalf of
the father, the father's the one who's going to be collecting the
כתובה. ketubah. So basically you're arguing on behalf of the person who
knows the information, the woman, and whose body it occurred to, is
the one making the claim because she can claim that this מום
mum came later, but it's for the sake of somebody who doesn't
know the information and whose body it didn't happen to, the father.
So that weakens her claim, okay? And therefore he has to prove
it, she's got to say that she's got to really prove that
it came later. רישא, Reisha, מנה
לאבא בידך.
mana l'abba
biyadeich. You are my father $100. The סיפא seifa in the end
after נישואין, nissuin, she's her own person. So then once she's arguing
she's saying מנה לי בידך, mana li biyadeich, okay, you owe me
$100, and since she's making the claim for herself after נישואין, nissuin,
then she's in a stronger position. All right, so that's his answer.
Now the גמרא Gemara has a question. איתיביה רב אחא בריה דרב
אוויא לרב אשי. eitvei Racha brei d'Rav Avya l'Rav Ashi. So רב
אחא בריה דרב אוויא Racha brei d'Rav Avya asks רב אשי Rav
Ashi about this ברייתא, brayta, תוספתא Tosefta that asked billions of questions,
could do question on anyone, not just on רב אשי. Rav Ashi.
Let's take a look. מודה רבי מאיר במומין הראויין לבוא עמה מבית
אביה שעל האב להביא ראיה. modeh Rabbi Meir b'mumin ha-ra'uyin l'voin imma
mibeit aviha she-al ha-av lehavi re'ayah. So רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir concedes.
The whole question of who's he conceding to? Because it doesn't seem
connected to the debate of רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir and the חכמים
chachamim in the משנה. Mishnah. Let's not worry about that. But anyway,
here's a point that it is true that when she has a
מום mum that would naturally be assumed to come from her from
the father's house, שעל האב להביא ראיה, she-al ha-av lehavi re'ayah, that
it becomes the father's responsibility. So even if it's found in the
husband's house, we assume it means this, but if it's the type
of a מום mum that could have been there from before, right?
If it's not a more recently developed מום, mum, it's the type
of a מום mum that it's reasonable to assume was there from
before, then it becomes the father's responsibility to prove that it existed
after the קידושין. kiddushin Okay, so גמרא Gemara says why is that?
We've been saying that it's always going to be the husband's responsibility.
So גמרא Gemara says, אמאי מנה לי בידך הוא? amai mana li
biyadeich hu? Why not say like you've been saying that once she's
in the husband's house, she's making a claim on her own behalf
and even though it's possible this מום mum pre-existed, it's possible that
it's new. Even if it's possible that it cropped up in the
father's house, it could have cropped up after the קידושין. Kiddushin? So
you know this basically changes everything. Until now we've been saying once
it's in the husband's house, it's the husband's burden of responsibility. Now
we're saying oh no, but if it's a type of מום mum
that could have been from before, it's not the husband's responsibility. Why
not? How's all the other arguments we made not legitimate arguments? Just
because it's possible it's from before, you don't know it's from before.
Maybe it came from after the קידושין. kiddushin, So the גמרא's Gemara
answer is, and now Michael's going to be very happy, the גמרא's
Gemara answer is: הכא במאי עסקינן ביותרת. hacha bemai askinan biyateret. It's
something like congenital, it's like an extra finger. Okay, so if it's
congenital, okay, then of course it doesn't matter whose house it was
discovered in. I mean, I don't know how you set it with
an extra toe, okay, but if it was congenital then who cares
whose house it was discovered in? It pre-existed and therefore it was
before the קידושין kiddushin and the husband wins. So that's what we're
talking about. So גמרא Gemara says יותרת? yateret? מאי ראיה מייתי? mai
re'ayah mayti? So if that's true, what does it mean, oh, now
it's the כלה kallah and the father's responsibility to bring a proof?
What proof could they bring? Obviously it was from the time of
the קידושין, kiddushin it's an extra toe! גמרא Gemara says no, what
proof are they bringing? מאי ראיה מייתי? mai re'ayah mayti? Why is
it relevant? No, then they can try to bring evidence that no,
he knew about it, like she showed him the extra toe, with
witnesses that she showed him the extra toe! I don't care about
that! That would be the evidence, okay? So now what the גמרא
Gemara has produced to end is that it matters if it's congenital,
obviously that changes everything, then of course it was there at the
time of the קידושין Kiddushin, and the only question is can you
prove that he was okay with it. Okay, but presumably if it's
not congenital, then even though it's possible she had it for a
very long time, then of course he has the burden of proof.
And bottom line the משנה Mishnah said if it's found in her
house, she has the burden of proof, if it's found after the
חופה, chuppah. he has the burden of proof. What's the difference? So
we basically have two answers. One answer was that after the חופה
chuppah. that creates a חזקה, chazakah, a presumption that he was okay
with it, and now that shifts the burden of proof, okay, or
another answer is whether she's making a claim for her father or
making a claim for herself. Alright, yes. This entire סוגיא sugya presumes
something about her age. Should she be a בוגרת? bogeret? Oh yeah,
if she would be a בוגרת, bogeret, so if it's the issue
whether she's making a claim for herself or her father, then being
a בוגרת bogeret would make a difference because she would be making
a claim for herself even before the חופה. chuppah. If the issue
was that the act of the חופה chuppah, creates a presumption that
he was okay with it, then it wouldn't matter she's a בוגרת.
bogeret. You're right. So that would be a big difference based on
those two answers. Okay, now we're going to talk about a, now
since we have this case so clear, we're going to talk about
an analogous case, okay, and see how we can apply it or
not. אמר רב יהודה אמר שמואל, Amar Rav Yehuda amar Shmuel, אמר
רב יהודה אמר שמואל. said Rav Yehuda in the name of Shmuel.
המוכר פרה בחמור. Hamocher parah bachamor. Okay, so I am changing to,
you know, sell you my cow for your donkey. This is like
a קידושין? Kiddushin, Exactly. ומשך בעל החמור את הפרה. U'mashach ba'al hachamor
et haparah. So, no, excuse me, I'm buying your cow for my
donkey. I'm buying your cow for my donkey. So I go ahead
and I take your cow, I take Bessie into my barn. Like
bartering? Right, no, right, swapping. Anyway, I go ahead and I take
Bessie into my barn, okay, and I haven't yet delivered my donkey.
ומשך בעל החמור את הפרה. U'mashach ba'al hachamor et haparah. So since
the owner of the donkey pulled the cow, now you, Charlie, you
own Bessie, and now you just gave Bessie to me, and now
you have not yet come and taken the donkey, my donkey, from
me, okay, and we go back to my yard to get my
donkey, and what do we discover? עד שמת החמור. Ad she'meit hachamor.
And when we go to get the donkey, we find that the
donkey has died. Okay, so there we were, it was twelve noon,
you gave me Bessie. Then we walk over to my house, it's
twelve-thirty, and we see that the donkey is dead. So the question
is when did the donkey die? If the donkey died after twelve
o'clock, then Charlie, it was your donkey that died and that's your
problem, right? If the donkey died before twelve o'clock, then when I
took Bessie there, it was a dead donkey and the deal was
off. Okay, so the question is when did the donkey die? After
the deal was sealed and final, because as soon as I took
Bessie, that finalized the deal. But if the donkey is dead, obviously
it's not a good deal. Or it died after the deal went
through and you're stuck with a dead donkey. It's like double hearsay,
right? Like maybe he concealed this was like... Alright, so we'll assume
that not. It got struck by lightning. We discover, okay, we discover
that a car hit it, whatever. Let's bracket all the other variables.
Okay, so what's the הלכה? halacha? Who has the burden of proof,
me or you, to prove when the donkey died? So you even
know one thing. The donkey does not have the burden of proof.
Exactly, although it is a beast of burden. That's a good one.
Okay, so על בעל החמור להביא ראיה שהיה חמורו קיים בשעת משיכת
פרה. Al ba'al hachamor lehavi ra'ayah shehayah chamoro kayam b'sha'at meshichat parah.
I have the burden of proof to prove to you that my
donkey was still alive when I took the cow and to prove
that the sale went through. Now that's a little bit funny, because
think about what we should assume. As far as everybody saw, at
the time that we did the deal, there was a presumption that
it was a good sale. Also, I'm in possession of the cow,
right? So I'm in possession of the cow and there's a presumption
of a good sale and we're saying nevertheless, we have to assume
the sale is no good until I can prove that the sale
actually went through. Okay, that the donkey died later. That's right. Why?
Is it because there's a חזקה chazakah. of the donkey being alive?
Right, that's a third point too, that the presumption, all those things
are in my favor. Nevertheless, I have, that's a good point. So
there's three presumptions. A, there's a presumption it was a good sale.
B, I'm in possession of the cow. So that should count for
a lot
because now
you're going to
have to try to take the cow away from me. And right,
and then there's a presumption that the donkey just died at the
last moment, חזקת חיה, chascas chaya, חזקת הגוף,
and all those things, and nevertheless,
I have to prove it. So that's pretty strong. Now let's say
the כלה Kallah under the חופה chuppah and see... Well, let's take
a look. Exactly. So the גמרא Gemara starts to say, תנא טונא,
Tana tuna, and we taught our משנה, Mishnah, our משנה Mishnah supports
this, the משנה Mishnah of the כלה, Kallah, which is our משנה.
Mishnah. So the גמרא Gemara says, הי כלה? Hi Kallah? Which case
of the כלה, Kallah, because there's a case where it's her proof
and there's a case where it was the husband's proof? אילימא כלה
בבית אביה. Eileima Kallah b'veis aviha. Okay, if it's the place where
the כלה Kallah was in the father's house and it's her proof.
Okay, so what do we see there? In that case, we see
she's coming to take out the money and she's got the burden
of proof. Okay, but she's got the burden of proof because she's
coming to take money from the husband. מי דמי? Mi dami? How
could you compare it? התם מייתי אראיה ומפסיד. Hatam maisi a'ra'aya u'mafsid.
There the father has to... There the father has to bring the
proof in order to extract money. הכא Hacha מייתי בעל חמרא maisei
ba'al chamra ומעכב. umakeiv. Here you're saying the owner of the donkey
has to bring the burden of proof to keep the cow. So,
that's not similar, that doesn't, that seems to be a very different
case that you need to bring the proof. So, אמר רבה Amar
Rabbah סיפא, seiyfa, let's go to the second case, he's going with
a reverse strategy, under the assumption that the first half and the
second half of the משנה Mishnah are arguing with one another. So
let's ignore the first half, let's just focus on the second half
of the משנה, Mishnah, where it's the חתן's chasan obligation. So the
חתן chasan is the one who has the money, and nevertheless, it's
his burden of proof. So that's similar to this case of the
cow and the donkey. I got the cow, but I still have
to prove it was a good sale. So the גמרא Gemara says,
אמר ליה רב חנינא Amar leh Rav Chanina וכי לא דמי, ve-chi
lo dami, it's not so similar. התם Hasam בעל מייתי ראיה ba'al
maisei ra'aya ומלי ליה חזקת דאבא. umali leh chezkas d'ava. Okay, there,
why does the husband have a burden of proof? Because the father
and the bride have a חזקה. chazakah. What חזקה chazakah do they
have? A חזקת הגוף which makes us presume that the blemish occurred
only at the latest time possible. So if there's a responsibility, if
there's an obligation of proof, a burden of proof on the husband
even though he's the one with the money, it's because there's an
argument in favor of the bride that the blemish came you know
later, she has a חזקת הגוף. That's why the husband could have
the burden of proof. הכא Hacha בעל החמור מייתי ראיה, ba'al ha-chamor
maisei ra'aya, here you're telling the owner of the donkey has to
bring proof, not only that he already has the cow, but also
ומוקים חזקה דידיה, umokim chazakah didei, by saying that he's the one
that has the חזקה, chazakah like he's the one that has the
presumption the donkey died later. So it's crazy. He's got the cow,
there's a presumption the donkey died later, that's dissimilar to other cases
in the משנה. Mishnah. Whoever has the obligation of proof in the
משנה Mishnah has one thing going against him, either they don't have
the money or they don't have the חזקה. chazakah In this case,
he's both got the money and the חזקה. chazakah, Okay, right. So,
אמר רב נחמן בר יצחק Amar Rav Nachman bar Yitzchak כלה בבית
אביה kala be-veis aviha וקידושין. u-le-kiddushin. Ah, no. We're going to get
it from when she's in the father's house and she has the
burden of proof. So she doesn't, so she has the חזקה chazakah
going for her, nevertheless she has the burden of proof. But why
does she have the burden of proof? Because she's coming to take
money from the חתן. chasan. No, there's one money that she's not
coming to take from the חתן, chasan, she's just trying to keep
her own that she already had and she's trying to keep. You
know what she's trying to keep that she's already
got? The פרוטה perutah that was given over for קידושין, Kiddushin, the
ring.
Okay, so he's trying to say the תנאי tnai
wasn't met, the קידושין Kiddushin wasn't never binding, not only am I
not paying you כתובה kesubah give me back my ring. And she's
saying no the blemish came later and now
you got to divorce me you got to give me the כתובה
kesubah and I'm keeping my ring. So in that case when we
look at the question of the ring, okay, she's got the חזקה
chazakah, in her favor, she's got the חזקת הגוף that the blemish
came later, she's got the ring in her possession, and we're assuming
that she's got to make proof her case even just to keep
the ring. So similarly in this case, he's got the cow in
his possession, he's got the חזקה
chazakah
that the donkey died later, nevertheless if
you want to keep the cow, you want to keep the thing
that was given to you on the assumption that this was a
good transaction, you've got the burden- now
it doesn't explain why logically why, if you've got the חזקה,
chazakah
חזקת ממון chezkas mamon
and the חזקה chazakah why should you have to? But somehow we're
saying since the ring or the cow was only given to you
on the presumption that it was a good transaction, we don't look
at you as if you're really in possession of the ring, you're
really in possession of the cow because that's exactly what the question
is: whether it was a good transaction, whether it really is yours.
It's different when the wife wants to take money from me, it
clearly was
my money, she's
just saying that I have to pay the כתובה, kesubah, but there
is no question that's my money, she's just claiming that I now
have a debt to her. But in terms of the ring or
the cow is that really you know the- was that really the
bride's ring, was that really the guy's cow? That's what's the question
here, whether it was a good transaction, whether it really is yours.
So that whole thing is similar that even though you have the
ring and you got the cow and even though you got a
חזקה, chazakah you still have the
burden of proof because it
really isn't your ring yet, it really isn't your cow yet, that's
what's the question is. So even there you have- so the same
way we're going
to assume that the כלה kallah has to prove in order to
keep the ring even though she's got a חזקה chazakah. in her
favor that the blemish came later, here too the guy's got to
prove to keep the cow even though he's got a חזקה but
the donkey died later. So that clearly indicates that his giving her
the ring and his being מכניס machnis her into חופה chuppah, are
really two different things according to קידושין Kiddushin and נישואין. nisuin. No
no no, I thought the meant, in other words because otherwise you
could make a parallel argument, in other words in other words he
gave the ring, you brought her into the חופה, chuppah, you have
to assume that that was okay with him. No no no you're
going back to חזקה in and whatever, but we're not. So anyway,
we're
going even in the case where it was found
before the חופה. Okay?
And it's found in her house, she's got a burden of proof.
There's no חופה. It's קידושין, Kiddushin a day later it was discovered
or whatever, or that's the issue. Let's, well let's see the answer
given בסוף שמונה. besof shemonah. Okay? So וקידושין, u-kiddushin, ולא תימא ליה
דמאן דאמר קידושין לאו לטיבועא ניתנו velo teima lei deman de-amar kiddushin
lav letivu'a nitnu there is a debate in the גמרא Gemara. whether,
what's the story? Like you know there's a big question, right? If
an engagement breaks off, does she have to give the engagement ring
back? Does she have to give the gifts back that were given
throughout that whole dating period? So this is a question in the
גמרא. Gemara Do we say the קידושין, Kiddushin. meaning the money given
for the קידושין, Kiddushin I'll call it the ring, was sort of
sunk in the ocean, לטיבועא, letivu'a, to be sunk, or not? Meaning
once you give it, even if for some reason, let's say, let's
say here's another scenario the גמרא Gemara deals with. The guy gives
it and then he drops dead. Before there was a חופה. There
was no חופה. He drops dead. So what do we assume? Do
we assume that he was only giving the ring on the presumption
that it would continue until the חופה, and if it didn't continue
until the חופה she's got to give the ring back to the
estate cause the guy dropped dead a day later? Or do we
assume no, he gave it and that was meant for her to
keep whatever was to happen afterwards? That's the question whether we say
the ring is given לטיבועא letivu'a and therefore whatever happens afterwards she
keeps it, or it's not given לטיבועא. letivu'a. So it goes like
this: ולא תימא ליה דמאן דאמר קידושין לאו לטיבועא ניתנו. velo teima
lei deman de-amar kiddushin lav letivu'a nitnu. Not this is not only
going, the idea that whether, you know, whether there was a blemish
or not a blemish, she has to give the ring back.
No, it only goes to the one that says that the ring
isn't given לטיבועא. letivu'a. אלא אפילו למאן דאמר קידושין לטיבועא ניתנו, ella
afilu leman de-amar kiddushin letivu'a nitnu, even according to the idea that
says the ring was given לטיבועא, letivu'a, meaning that if afterwards for
example he dies and there's no חופה, she keeps the ring. Even
so, that's not in this case. הני מילי קידושי ודאי, hanei mili
kiddushei vadai, that's when the קידושין Kiddushin. is definitely good, and then
like I said he died the day after, then maybe she could
keep the ring. אבל קידושי טעות, aval kiddushei ta'ut, but in this
case the point was, there was no קידושין Kiddushin in the first
place! I made a condition and the קידושין wasn't good! I don't
want you to keep the ring if there was never קידושין. Whereas
it was, once it was קידושין keep the ring no matter what
happens afterwards, but here there was no קידושין. אי מייתי ראיה אין,
ei meiti re'aya in, if she
can
prove that the קידושין was good and the blemish came later, then
she can keep the ring. ואי לא לא, ve-ei lo lo, and
if not, no. Okay?
So here basically the argument is that in this case of
the כלה, kallah, she's got to prove it when it's
found in her house, even just to keep the ring. Because even
by the ring she's not really considered in full physical possession since
it came from him and contextually the question is whether that was
a good transaction or not. She's not considered in full possession of
it and she has to prove it, even though she has a
חזקה on herself. And similarly by the case of the donkey
and the cow, even though he's in possession of the cow, okay,
since his possession of the cow is only because of the presumption
that the transaction worked, he's got to prove that the transaction was
good. Okay, so now let's see, the תוספות are asking on this,
מחט שנמצאת בעובי בית הכוסות. machat shenimtzeit be-ovi beit hakosot. If you
have a, this is a טריפה treifa issue, it's really a question
of חזקה. If you've got a pin, a needle, thank you, that
was found in the thickness of like the flaps of this is
one of the stomachs here of the cow, where basically it's like
these folded flaps of skin. And only if the needle goes, the
hole that goes all the way through all the flaps, right, into
the inner organ, is it considered a טריפה. treifa. If it only
goes through, you know, the outer skin, the outer flaps but doesn't
pierce all the way through, it's not a טריפה. treifa. So you
find this needle, מצד אחד כשרה. mitzad echad kesherah. If the hole
is only on one side, it's כשרה. kesherah. משני צדדים טריפה, mishnei
tzedadim treifa, if it goes through both sides, the animal is a
טריפה. treifa. נמצא עליה קורט דם, nimtza aleha koret dam, if there's
a drop of blood, בידוע שהוא לפני שחיטה, beyadu'a shehu lifnei shechitah,
then we know it came from before שחיטה shechitah and it's a
טריפה. treifa. לא נמצא עליה קורט דם, lo nimtza aleha koret dam,
if there's no drop of blood on the needle, right, then בידוע
שהוא לאחר שחיטה, beyadu'a shehu le-achar shechitah, then the only reason it
made a hole is if it came after שחיטה. shechitah. Now, הוגלד,
huglad, now let's say there is a drop of blood and... The
blood has now crusted over, okay? פי המכה. Pi hamaka. So it's
crusted, so now yes, it's crusted over the opening of the wound.
So, it's a scab. Scab, this blood. So clearly it was from
before שחיטה. shechita. But here's the question: is it before שחיטה, shechita,
but was it before or after I sold it to Charlie? Okay,
Charlie bought it a week ago, okay, so, or he bought it
two days ago, right? And we know that it got this problem
before שחיטה, shechita, but it's sort of like when did the donkey
die? When did it swallow this pin, or this this needle, before
or after I sold it to him? Okay, so, באודא דהאי אית
דאספלא, bi'uda d'hai it d'aspla, באוש דתלתא יומי קודם שחיטה. ba'osh d'tlasha
yomi kodem shechita. Then a scab takes three days. So if I
sold it to Charlie within the last two days and after שחיטה
shechting it you found a scab, then we know the problem was
out when I sold it to him
and he has to give us money back.
ולא איגלי פי המכה, V'lo igli pi hamaka, if it
hasn't scabbed over, and then we don't know, it's not scabbed and
I sold it to him two days ago, so we know
it didn't happen three days ago, but did it happen two days
ago or one day ago, right? When did this, we know that
it was before שחיטה, shechita, we know it happened recently, but we
don't know whether before or after I sold it to Charlie. So
what's the הלכה? halacha? המוציא מחבירו עליו הראיה. Hamotzi meichaveiro alav hara'aya.
Charlie you want your
money back, you prove to me that that that thing was there
from before I sold it to you. Okay, what? והא דהכא קמייתי?
V'ha d'hacha kamayti? So is it that he brings it? Okay. Okay,
it's basically means that
I... now, isn't this similar to the case of the cow and
the donkey? Right? I got the cow, and so on, right? In
this case, you know, if you want to get your cow back,
you prove
to me when the donkey died. Right? And here it's the same
thing, right? So if Charlie wants to get his money back, he
gave me the money, prove to me
when the animal became a טריפה. treifa. So that seems like the
burden of proof is on the one who wants to take the
money away, which is not what שמואל Shmuel says. שמואל Shmuel said
that even though I've got the cow, I have the burden of
proof. So the גמרא Gemara says, he wants to take the money
or
the cow, who has to get the cow back? No, in the
case of the cow there was no money. It was a cow
for a donkey, so the cow was like the money. You had
the cow as like the money. Yeah the cow was like the
money. Right, right, yeah yeah yeah. Okay so basically this rules that
if you want to reverse it, you know, then you've got if
you want your money back you prove it, if you want your
cow back you prove it. Okay so the גמרא Gemara says, אי
הכי האי שוחט דמי. ei hachi hai shocheit damei. So if Charlie
is the שוחט shocheit and he wants his money back, אייתי ראיה,
ayti ra'aya, he has to bring the proof to get his money
back. So that why, how's that different than the cow and the
donkey? דאמאי, De'amai, בעל הבהמה ליתי ראיה ולשקול. ba'al ha'beheima leisei ra'aya
v'lishkol. So according to שמואל'ס Shmuel's argument, it should be my responsibility
to prove that the sale was binding, right? You get it? The
money is sort of like receiving the cow, right? Right, you got
it? So I have the money. So if שמואל Shmuel said that
when I got the cow I still have to prove it was
a good sale when there was a dead donkey,
if
I've
got the money according to שמואל Shmuel then I have to prove
it was a good sale. So the גמרא Gemara says, no we're
talking דלא יהא תפס דמי, de'lo yei tafas damei, we don't really
mean that the שוחט shocheit has to bring proof and
that if he gave the money he has to bring the proof.
He didn't give the money. What we really say
is שמואל Shmuel didn't give the money, and
if I want to get
the money from Charlie I've got to prove it, but no what
we're saying is it goes totally against the simple reading of the
משנה. Mishna. Like this מסכת maseches or this ברייתא, beraisa, this ברייתא
beraisa said, the guy if you want your money back you bring
the proof. And the גמרא Gemara says,
which is exactly against
שמואל. Shmuel.
And the גמרא Gemara says that's not what it means. What it
really means is the opposite. It really means that that the guy
who I sold him the cow, I'm the one who sold him
the cow, whether I have the money or don't have the money,
I have the burden of proof. Okay, to make it consistent with
שמואל. Shmuel. That the guy, you know, that I've got to prove
to Charlie that it was an okay sale, even if I've got
the money or not. So the גמרא Gemara says, במאי פסקא? b'mai
piska? What allows you to say that the ברייתא beraisa here is
talking like it says the burden of proof is on the one
who, you know, who's come to take the money. You're trying to
say that's not what it means, that's not what it means but
what allows you to sort of read it that it's always the
seller who's got the burden of proof, right? That's not what the
משנה Mishna said. במאי פסקא B'mai piska means what allows what allows
you to sort of make this פשט? p'shat? This is like make
the משנה Mishna categorical. The משנה Mishna said the burden of proof
is on the person who's coming to take out the money.
And you're saying it's not the person who's coming to take out
the money. It would be a case where the money hasn't been
paid and it really means that the burden of proof is always
on the seller. What allows you to read the משנה Mishna like
that? Okay, אלא, so it seems that that's clearly a case where
the burden of proof logically is on the one who doesn't have
the, you know, you know who's coming to take out the money.
So if either Charlie wants his money back he has to bring
proof, if Charlie wants his cow back and there's a dead donkey,
he has to prove it. What do you mean by categorically? What
do you mean by referring to the categorical? Meaning that the משנה,
Mishnah, well let's do the other. אלא כי אתא רב יצחק בר
שמואל בר מרתא אמר, ela ki ata Rav Yitzchak bar Shmuel bar
Marta amar, and רב יצחק בר שמואל Rav Yitzchak bar Shmuel came
and said, לא תציתו להו
להני כללי דכייל יהודה אחי משמיה דשמואל,
lo ttzitu
lehu
lehani klalei dechayil Yehuda achi mishmeih deShmuel, as he's quoted
by רב יהודה Rav Yehuda in his name. He says don't listen
to the principles that יהודה Yehuda my brother said in my name,
because they were brothers. הכי אמר שמואל. hachi amar Shmuel. So forget
everything he said, what he said was wrong. Because it's crazy right
what he was saying? Why shouldn't be the responsibility of the guy
who, who, who sold the donkey? He now has a cow in
his possession. This is what שמואל Shmuel really said: כל שנולד ספק
ברשותו עליו הראיה. kol shenolad safek birshuto alav haraayah. Wherever the sort
of doubt arose, that's who has the proof. What's that mean? ודתניא
כלה, vedetanya kallah, and things like this by the case of כלה.
kallah. So for the case of the כלה kallah we're going back
to that earlier explanation, like with A, but if the donkey die,
if, if the מום mum is found in the כלה's kallah house,
she has the ראיה. raayah. If the מום mum is found in
the חתן's chatan house after the נשואין, nisuin, he's got the burden
of proof. So similarly here, what would be the translation here by
the case of the donkey? So the case would be, let me
just check, what רש"י Rashi says, the donkey, hold on. Yeah, so
רש"י Rashi goes basically same point here, it's because since I took
the cow into my possession, okay, once I took the cow into
my possession there's a, it's not exactly the same, because here we
don't really know, was it at her father's house or was it
at her groom's house? But here conceptually it's when I took the
cow to my possession, there's a presumption that now it's your donkey.
Since there's a presumption that it's your donkey, that it was a
good seller and then we find a dead donkey, that's life. It's
a problem that came up with you, there's a presumption you own
the donkey, we found a dead donkey, that's your problem. If you
want to prove that it was the opposite, you have the burden
of proof. Do you get it? When the כלה kallah is found
with a מום mum in the father's house, it's her problem, she's
got to prove, if the מום mum is found after the חופה,
it's his problem, he's got to prove. So in parallel, I took
the cow, you're presumed to own the donkey, we find a dead
donkey, that's your problem.
And if you want to prove it's something else,
you said right, that's exactly the opposite of what's quoted before in
the name of שמואל. Shmuel. If you want to prove opposite, you've
got the burden of proof, okay? Let's just go to the תוד"ה,
Tosafos Dibbur Hamatchil, okay? So the גמרא Gemara says, ודתניא מחט הנמצאת
בעובי בית הכוסות וכו', vedetanya machat hanimtzet be'ovi beit hakosot vechu', די
בלאו הכי טבח דמי. de belav hachi tabach damei. So here by
that case about the מום, mum, it's not a question of whose
רשות. reshus. It's a question of who's got the money. Charlie has
got the cow, okay, he שחט. shacht. He finds the hole in
it. So the problem occurred in Charlie's domain. It was his cow,
now he has the cow, he שחט shacht it, he found the
problem. But nonetheless, that ברייתא braisa says who's got the burden of
proof? The person who wants to extract the money. So if Charlie
hasn't paid me yet, who's got the burden of proof? I have
the burden of proof. Like if he hasn't paid me, if I
want to get his money. So that's not the question of whose
domain did it occur in. That's the simple question of who wants
the money, who needs to be paid, right? So the גמרא Gemara
says, ואי דלאו הכי טבח דמי, ve'ee delav hachi tabach damei, if
Charlie hasn't paid the money, בא המוכר להביא ראיה ויוציא, ba hamocher
lehavi raayah veyotzi, I have to bring the proof if I want
to get the money out of Charlie. This is what we normally
say, the guy who wants to take, get the money is the
one who's got the burden of proof. ואמאי? ve'amai? According to you,
that's not the logic. The logic is not who wants to get
the money, the logic is where did the problem occur? ספק ברשות
טבח נולד. safek birshus tabach nolad. So the problem was discovered in
the cow when he went, Charlie already had the cow and שחט
shacht it, so that's clearly defined as Charlie's problem. So the גמרא
Gemara says no, דפרע דמי. depara damei. We're talking in the case,
we're only talking in the case where Charlie's already paid
money.
And since Charlie's already paid the money, when you say the burden
of proof is the one who wants to extract the money, it's
merely saying that Charlie always has the burden of proof.
Okay, it's sort of like what we tried to do before, we
take a ברייתא, braisa, the ברייתא braisa says it's about who wants
to get the money, we say no no, we're talking about a
case where it's presumed that Charlie paid the money.
So it's just a way of saying Charlie always has the burden
of proof. Now why not say Charlie's got the burden of proof?
Okay, the גמרא Gemara says, ומאי פסקא, umai piska, like I said
before, what allows you to
sort of say categorically, you know, that every time it's about who
wants to collect the
money, what allows you to read it that it's only in the
case that Charlie paid the money that really means that Charlie's always
the one who has to prove it? סתמא דמילתא stama demilsa says
no, because we can presume that סתמא דמילתא stama demilsa הכי קים
להו לרבנן דאין אדם נותן פרה אלא אם כן נטל דמיה, hachi
kim lehu lerabanan de'ein adam noten parah ela im ken natal dameha,
because the normal thing is that Charlie is assumed to be always
the one who has paid the money because I don't give you
my cow unless I get the cash. Okay, so what it means
is that we've really got, oh right now we're going to look
closely, but what we've really got is that. It started by this
very bizarre idea that the guy who sold the cow, sold the
donkey, he's got the cow in his possession, he's got the חזקת
הגוף and all of that, but he has to go ahead and
prove it. That doesn't make- didn't make any sense. We normally
say if you want to extract the money you've got to prove
it. We had the case for extracting the money but a case
from the end that
became the טריפה, treifa, so we reversed it.
But we didn't fully reverse
it to
say whoever is trying to extract the money needs to prove
it. We said wherever the problem crops up, that's where the burden
of proof is. So if the problem crop up in her house,
she's got the burden of proof. If they crop up in his
house, he's got the burden of proof. The problem is, it didn't
stay in with the case about the- the case of the טריפה.
treifa. Because the case of the טריפה treifa said a more normal
principle, which is: if you want to say it was not a
good sale or whatever, if you-
whoever has to- wants to take money from somebody else, they have
the burden of proof. If Charlie's already paid me and he wants
to reverse the sale, he's got to prove it. If he
hasn't paid me and I want- and I want to
prove
that it was a good sale, I've got the burden of proof.
Okay, so that's the way it sounded like. But the question was:
who's trying to take the money?
And we wanted to say no, it really means that Charlie, since
the problem was found with the animal when Charlie was שחטינג shechting
it and it's Charlie's possession, he always- that's where it was found,
that's where the burden of proof is. The burden is always on
Charlie. Even- so I can even make Charlie pay, even when he
hasn't paid yet, he's got the burden of proof. So why did
it say oh, the one who wants to get the money back
is the one who has the burden? It didn't mean the one
who wants to get the money back. It really means the butcher
who has this burden of proof. It describes him as
the one who wants to get the money back because it presumes
that the butcher wouldn't have the cow unless he had paid the
money. But it really didn't mean it. That's what- I know, that's
what- that's what bothered the גמרא before. Its legal principle is: the
butcher has to bring the proof. Say: the butcher has to bring
the proof! Don't say: the one who wants to extract the money.
Oh, and of course we mean the butcher because we're assuming the
butcher's the one who's already paid the money. And so what you
really have is you really have these two different approaches. What you
got, the first one that seemed to make no sense, but even
in the end you've got one approach that really powers this: the
burden of proof is- is on the person who had- where the
problem was discovered, and you have the more standard approach is: the
burden of proof is on the person who wants to extract the
money.